# **Thomas Harrop**

## twharrop@gmail.com · tomharrop.io

I am a post-doctoral researcher with a background in bioinformatics, genetics and molecular biology and interests in data science and research relating to agriculture. I mainly work with R, Python and shell scripts. I have experience in molecular, plant, animal and medical laboratories and installing, maintaining and using computers running Unix, Linux and macOS.

### Personal information

Nationalities Australian and British

**Research** My research interests include plant and insect research

related to agronomy, tools and techniques in bioinformatics

and evolutionary and comparative biology.

Technical My main tools are R, Python and bash. I also use Markdown, TeX,

html and css.

I use git and GitHub for version control and strive to follow the principles of reproducible research when coding.

I have experience with workload managers for highperformance computing (HPC) including SGE and LSF and maintain an installation of SLURM on my own workstation.

I have built and used workstations and servers that run macOS, Ubuntu and FreeBSD, and run jobs in HPC environments running Debian and CentOS.

I have skills in molecular biology techniques including quantitative real-time PCR, cloning, nucleic acid extraction and cDNA library preparation, as well as classical genetic approaches with live organisms, such as transformation, crosses, microdissection and bioassays.

**Languages** English (native), German (TELC Level B2) and French (TELC

Level B1)

**About me** Outside work I enjoy building and riding bicycles, social

football and basketball, cooking, programming and technology.

## **Education**

2006-2012 Doctor of Philosophy, Department of Genetics, the
 University of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

 Thesis: The functions of cytochrome P450s in Drosophila.
 During my Ph.D. I used classical genetics and modern
 molecular biology, including transgenic manipulation of gene
 expression and comparative studies of gene function, to

Drosophila genus.

2002–2005 Bachelor of Science with Honours (first class), the University

investigate the functions of cytochrome P450 genes in the

of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

Awards 2006–2009, Australian Postgraduate Award

## **Experience**

## **Research positions**

2016- Post-doctoral researcher, Laboratory for Evolution and
 Present Development, Biochemistry Department, University of Otago,
 Dunedin, New Zealand.
 In my current position, I work on a bioprotection project
 investigating the resistance of Argentine stem weevil to its
 biological control agent.

2014–2016 Post-doctoral researcher, UMR DIADE, Institut de Recherche pour le Développement (IRD), Montpellier, France.

I used machine learning, data mining, statistical analyses and other bioinformatic techniques to study the development of inflorescence architecture in rice, which affects crop yield. We used laser microdissection and RNA sequencing to characterise molecular events that occur in the developing inflorescence, and applied these results to study the effects of selection on gene expression during the parallel domestications of African and Asian rice.

2013–2014 Post-doctoral researcher, Department of Plant Breeding and Genetics, Max Planck Institute for Plant Breeding Research, Cologne, Germany.

At the Max Planck Institute I worked on a bioinformatic and

At the Max Planck Institute I worked on a bioinformatic and molecular biology project to compare the transcriptional

response of different land plants to UV-B exposure, which acts as an environmental signal.

## **Professional positions**

2004-2007	Medical scientist, Network Pathology, the Austin Hospital,
	Heidelberg, Australia.

**2001–2004 Laboratory assistant**, Network Pathology, the Austin Hospital, Heidelberg, Australia.

### **Teaching**

2007-2011	3 <sup>rd</sup> Year Genetics, Department of Genetics, The University of
	Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

**2006–2009 High School Biology**, Department of Genetics, The University of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

**2006–2008 High School Biology**, Gene Technology Access Centre, The University High School, Parkville, Australia.

**2005–2008 1**<sup>st</sup> **Year Genetics**, The University of Melbourne, Parkville, Australia.

#### Students co-supervised

**Swarit Jaisal** Master of Science, Life Science Informatics, Universität Bonn, Germany.

**Axel Verdier** Master of Science, Sciences et Technologies de l'Information et de la Communication pour la Santé, Université de Montpellier, France.

#### **Publications**

## Peer-reviewed journals

Harrop, T.W.<sup>§</sup>, Denecke, S.<sup>§</sup>, Yang, Y.T., Chan, J., Daborn, P.J., Perry, T., Batterham, P., (2018). Evidence for activation of nitenpyram by a mitochondrial cytochrome P450 in *Drosophila melanogaster*. Pest Management Science 74, 1616–1622. doi:10.1002/ps.4852.

Ta, K. N., Adam. H., Staedler, Y.M., Schönenberger, J., Harrop. T.W.R., Tregear, J., Do, N.V., Gantet, P., Ghesquière, A., and Jouannic, S. (2017). Differences in meristem size and expression of branching genes are associated with variation in panicle phenotype in wild and domesticated African rice. EvoDevo 8: 2. <a href="doi:10.1186/s13227-017-0065-y">doi:10.1186/s13227-017-0065-y</a>.

- Harrop, T.W.R.§, Ud Din, I.§, Gregis, V., Osnato, M., Jouannic, S., Adam, H. and Kater, M. (2016). Gene expression profiling of reproductive meristem types in early rice inflorescences by laser microdissection. The Plant Journal 86, 75–88. doi:10.1111/tpj.13147.
- Harrop, T.W.R.<sup>§</sup>, Pearce, S.L.<sup>§</sup>, Daborn, P.J. and Batterham, P. (2014). Whole-genome expression analysis in the third instar larval midgut of *Drosophila melanogaster*. G3 (Bethesda) 4, 2197–2205. doi:10.1534/g3.114.013870.
- **Harrop, T.W.R.**, Sztal, T., Lumb, C., Good, R.T., Daborn, P.J., Batterham, P. and Chung, H. (2014). Evolutionary changes in gene expression, coding sequence and copy-number at the *Cyp6g1* locus contribute to resistance to multiple insecticides in Drosophila. Plos One 9, e84879. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0084879.
- Daborn, P.J., Lumb, C., **Harrop**, **T.W.R.**, Blasetti, A., Pasricha, S., Morin, S., Mitchell, S.N., Donnelly, M.J., Müller, P. and Batterham, P. (2012). Using *Drosophila melanogaster* to validate metabolism-based insecticide resistance from insect pests. Insect Biochemistry and Molecular Biology 42, 918–924. doi:10.1016/j.ibmb.2012.09.003.
- § Equal contribution

#### **Book chapters**

Cridge, A., **Harrop, T. W. R.**, Lovegrove, M., Remnant, E. & Dearden, P. (2017). *Nutrition and Epigenetic Change in Insects: Evidence and Implications*, in Advances in Insect Physiology (ed. Verlinden, H.) 53, 31–54 (Academic Press). <u>doi:10.1016/bs.aiip.2017.06.001</u>

#### Selected scientific presentations

- Comparative genomics of sexual and asexual parasitoid wasps from the Microctonus genus.

  Poster presentation at the 7<sup>th</sup> meeting of the European Society for Evolutionary Developmental Biology, Galway, Ireland, 2018.
- Genomics of a weevil pest and its parasitoid biocontrol agent. **Poster presentation** at the Annual Conference of the Genetics Society of Australasia (GSA) with the New Zealand Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (NZSBMB), Dunedin, New Zealand, 2017.
- De novo sequencing of Argentine stem weevil and its parasitoid wasp biocontrol agent. **Poster presentation** at the 10<sup>th</sup> Annual Arthropod Genomics Symposium, Notre Dame University, South Bend, U.S.A., 2017.
- Sequencing and community annotation of the Vespula vulgaris genome. **Oral presentation** at the Entomological Society of NZ Conference, Wellington, New Zealand, 2017.
- Genes controlling transition of reproductive meristem identity during inflorescence development. **Oral presentation** at the 14<sup>th</sup> International Symposium on Rice Functional Genomics, Montpellier, France, 2016.

- Mechanisms underlying the parallel evolution of inflorescence phenotype during independent domestication of African and Asian rice. **Contributed oral presentation** at the 6<sup>th</sup> meeting of the European Society for Evolutionary Developmental Biology, Uppsala, Sweden, 2016. **Joint symposium chair**: Branching across the tree of life.
- Gene expression during O. sativa panicle development. **Invited seminar** at the Agricultural Genetics Institute, Hanoi, Vietnam, 2015.
- Molecular mechanisms underlying the phenotypic convergence of inflorescence architecture in domesticated rice species. **Poster presentation** at the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution annual meeting, Vienna, Austria, 2015.
- Transcriptomic analysis of early developmental stages of the rice panicle. **Poster presentation** at the Workshop in Molecular Mechanisms Controlling Flowering, Aiguablava, Spain, 2015
- RNA interference of the Cytochrome P450 redox partners Cpr and dare uncovers novel P450 functions in Drosophila melanogaster. **Poster presentation** at the 50<sup>th</sup> Annual Drosophila Research Conference, Chicago, USA, 2009.

twharrop@gmail.com · tomharrop.io



Dunedin, NEW ZEALAND